<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-19T23:08:05-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">APUS Lab</title><subtitle>Multi-Disciplinary Analysis, Optimization, and Control</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Learning Coarse-Grained Dynamics on Graph</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_kuramoto/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Coarse-Grained Dynamics on Graph" /><published>2024-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/kuramoto</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_kuramoto/"><![CDATA[<p>“Heterogeneous networked dynamical systems with time-varying topologies” are universally seen in science and engineering - classical examples include power grids, molecule dynamics, and computational mechanics.  For the data-driven modeling of such systems, the brutal force approach is to use a time series model with a sufficiently deep <strong>graph neural network</strong> (GNN) with sufficiently long time-delay embedding (TDE) of past information.</p>

<p>To elucidate when and how such approach works, in our recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09324.pdf">ArXiv</a> manuscript, we systematically developed <strong>coarse-grained reduced-order models</strong> for networked dynamical systems.  Using the <strong>Mori-Zwanzig</strong> formalism, we quantify the impact of coarse-graining on the strength and distribution of interactions, and the required TDE length; subsequently we use this knowledge to rigorously design GNN architectures accordingly.  The approach is demonstrated on an academic Kuramoto example and a realistic power grid problem.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with <a href="https://jharlim.github.io/myhomepage/">Dr. John Harlim</a> from Math &amp; Meteorology and <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/yanli/">Dr. Yan Li</a> from EECS at Penn State.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2405_3.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="YinY" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Heterogeneous networked dynamical systems with time-varying topologies” are universally seen in science and engineering - classical examples include power grids, molecule dynamics, and computational mechanics. For the data-driven modeling of such systems, the brutal force approach is to use a time series model with a sufficiently deep graph neural network (GNN) with sufficiently long time-delay embedding (TDE) of past information.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modularized Bilinear Koopman Operator for Modeling and Predicting Transients of Microgrids</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_mkbf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modularized Bilinear Koopman Operator for Modeling and Predicting Transients of Microgrids" /><published>2024-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/mkbf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_mkbf/"><![CDATA[<p>We just published an <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10527356">article</a> in IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid, with the application of the so-called <strong>Koopman Bilinear Form</strong> (KBF) to networked system with inputs, such as the power grid.  Particularly, we (1) derive and incorporate conditions in KBF model to enforce SO(2) symmetry for accurate and long-term predictions, (2) make KBF model modularized to allow prediction in reconfigurable scenarios without retraining the model.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/yanli/">Dr. Yan Li</a> from Penn State EECS.  It is the published version of our prior arXiv paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.03214">here</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2405_1.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We just published an article in IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid, with the application of the so-called Koopman Bilinear Form (KBF) to networked system with inputs, such as the power grid. Particularly, we (1) derive and incorporate conditions in KBF model to enforce SO(2) symmetry for accurate and long-term predictions, (2) make KBF model modularized to allow prediction in reconfigurable scenarios without retraining the model.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Computational Science Minor Program</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/04/30/csci/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computational Science Minor Program" /><published>2024-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/04/30/csci</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/04/30/csci/"><![CDATA[<p>We recently took the responsibility in the supervision of the <a href="https://bulletins.psu.edu/undergraduate/colleges/engineering/computational-sciences-minor">Computational Science Minor program</a> offered by Penn State Aerospace Engineering.</p>

<p>This minor program provides the necessary skills to use computers to study and solve scientific, engineering and data-centric problems across a wide range of disciplines.  It was developed with numerical methods and onboard computing in mind back in the early 2000s, and now it evolves to encompass topics such as machine learning and artificial intelligence.</p>

<p>If you are interested, more details are <a href="https://csci.my.canva.site/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Course" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We recently took the responsibility in the supervision of the Computational Science Minor program offered by Penn State Aerospace Engineering.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winning NSF CAREER Award 2024</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/award_career/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winning NSF CAREER Award 2024" /><published>2024-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/career</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/award_career/"><![CDATA[<p>Supported by the NSF, we will develop “Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling for Control Co-Design of Morphing Aerial Autonomous Systems”.  This enables us to pursue our four research thrusts in a unified manner: integrate ROMs and control &amp; autonomy to achieve the <strong>full-stack design optimization</strong> of an engineering system.</p>

<p>University media coverage <a href="https://www.psu.edu/news/engineering/story/aerospace-engineering-researcher-daning-huang-awarded-nsf-career/">here</a>.  Project information <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2340266&amp;HistoricalAwards=false">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Supported by the NSF, we will develop “Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling for Control Co-Design of Morphing Aerial Autonomous Systems”. This enables us to pursue our four research thrusts in a unified manner: integrate ROMs and control &amp; autonomy to achieve the full-stack design optimization of an engineering system.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Jiwoo Song for winning the VFF Scholarship!</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/03/27/vff/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Jiwoo Song for winning the VFF Scholarship!" /><published>2024-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-03-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/03/27/vff</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/03/27/vff/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://verticalmag.com/press-releases/vertical-flight-society-announces-2024-scholarship-recipients/">Vertical Flight Foundation (VFF) Scholarship</a>, administered by the Vertical Flight Society, is awarded every year to the world’s most talented engineering students interested in vertical flight.  Since 1977, nearly 700 scholarships have been awarded.</p>

<p>This year, Jiwoo is among the 12 recipients in the Masters’ category.  This marks a good start of his journey of Ph.D. to <a href="/rsch_rotor/">rotorcraft blade optimization</a>.  Congratulations!</p>

<p>Also, among the total of 29 VFF scholarships (Bachelor, Master’s, and Ph.D.), five are Penn State students.  We Are!</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="JiwooS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Vertical Flight Foundation (VFF) Scholarship, administered by the Vertical Flight Society, is awarded every year to the world’s most talented engineering students interested in vertical flight. Since 1977, nearly 700 scholarships have been awarded.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modal Analysis of Spatiotemporal Data via Multivariate Gaussian Process Regression</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_mvgpr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modal Analysis of Spatiotemporal Data via Multivariate Gaussian Process Regression" /><published>2024-03-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-03-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/mvgpr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_mvgpr/"><![CDATA[<p>We just published a manuscript on <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.13118.pdf">ArXiv</a> for an innovative application of multi-variate Gaussian process regression to the modal analysis of spatiotemporal data, such as unsteady flow fields.  Our method is particularly suitable for the cases where the data set is scarce and/or the temporal sampling is irregular; in these cases, the conventional methods such as spectral proper orthogonal decomposition do not work well.  This is one of our efforts in one of our core thrusts, <a href="/rsch_std/">Scientific Data Analysis</a>.</p>

<p>This work is based on the Master’s thesis of our lab member, Jiwoo Song.  Good job, Jiwoo!</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2403_2.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="JiwooS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We just published a manuscript on ArXiv for an innovative application of multi-variate Gaussian process regression to the modal analysis of spatiotemporal data, such as unsteady flow fields. Our method is particularly suitable for the cases where the data set is scarce and/or the temporal sampling is irregular; in these cases, the conventional methods such as spectral proper orthogonal decomposition do not work well. This is one of our efforts in one of our core thrusts, Scientific Data Analysis.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Contributing to SIAM UQ24</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_uq24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Contributing to SIAM UQ24" /><published>2024-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/uq24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_uq24/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.siam.org/conferences/cm/conference/uq24">SIAM UQ24</a> occurs in Trieste, Italy.  While we could not be physically present there, we contribute a talk on physics-infused reduced-order modeling as part of a <a href="https://meetings.siam.org/sess/dsp_programsess.cfm?SESSIONCODE=78427">minisymposium</a>: “Recent Advances in Surrogate Modeling for UQ of Large-Scale Simulations”.</p>

<p>The central idea is that, conventional surrogates for UQ of dynamical systems only support a limited number of parameters, while we aim to leverage the PIROM methodology to build surrogates that are of <strong>infinite-dimensional</strong> parameters by directly encoding known dynamics into the model.  We connect this idea to the well-known Mori-Zwanzig formalism, and present two algorithms for learning PIROMs from data, that build on our lab member Carlos’ <a href="/rsch_pirom/">previous work</a>.</p>

<p>The slides are available <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1x7qbTt-A1IDZoZ3aJA57IObquPqfnu1T/view?usp=sharing">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="CarlosVV" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The SIAM UQ24 occurs in Trieste, Italy. While we could not be physically present there, we contribute a talk on physics-infused reduced-order modeling as part of a minisymposium: “Recent Advances in Surrogate Modeling for UQ of Large-Scale Simulations”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APUS at AIAA SciTech 2024</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_st24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APUS at AIAA SciTech 2024" /><published>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/st24</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_st24/"><![CDATA[<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2401_1.png" width="600" /></td>
      <td><br /><br /><img src="/img/post_2401_2.png" width="450" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>At the AIAA SciTech 2024 conference, we contributed six papers over a range of research fields, with our collaborators. Here are the summaries:</p>

<h2 id="operator-theoretic-methods-for-reduced-order-modeling">Operator-Theoretic Methods for Reduced-Order Modeling</h2>

<p>Dr. Huang and <a href="https://research.cec.sc.edu/wang">Dr. Yi Wang</a> co-organized a special session “Operator-Theoretic Methods for Reduced-Order Modeling in Structural Dynamics and Aeroelasticity” that focuses on the application of Koopman theory to nonlinear structural dynamics and aeroelasticity.  In this session, we contributed two papers:</p>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2266">Parametrized Global Linearization Models for Flutter Prediction</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jiwoo Song, Yin Yu, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>We provided an initial development of a rigorous framework for <strong>globally linearizing</strong> nonlinear flutter dynamics using the so-called <strong>Koopman Bilinear Form</strong>, and show that using partial measurements of pre-flutter dynamics one can construct a dynamical model, bilinear in system parameter, to <strong>predict the onset of flutter</strong>.  Demonstrated on a high-speed panel flutter problem.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/19v7fb7BjNnT6Pa9lzGaapFknpGgE2mDK/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2264">Residual Dynamic Mode Decomposition with Control for Nonlinear Aeroservoelastic Applications</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jacob C. Rains, Daning Huang, <a href="https://research.cec.sc.edu/wang">Yi Wang</a></li>
  <li>In parallel to the parametric model above, we also explore <strong>flutter dynamics with bilinear inputs</strong>, aiming to produce a unified, relatively simple yet accurate model for the <strong>flutter suppression</strong> in a wide range of flow conditions.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="physics-infused-reduced-order-modeling">Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling</h2>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-0782">Development of Weak-Form Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling With Applications</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Carlos Vargas Venegas, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>We continue to work on the PIROM, in an attempt to resolve the <a href="/rsch_pirom/"><strong>Impossible Trinity of Modeling</strong></a>.  The PIROM requires learning a differential equation from data, which can pose numerical challenge in training.  We proposed and demonstrated a weak-form formulation for <strong>accelerated learning</strong> of such models.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1KOTkdKiVIMmWndtTGZCfozqEhbprfZhv/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="high-speed-fluid-thermal-structural-interaction">High-Speed Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction</h2>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-1050">Reduced-Order Modeling for Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of Cone-Slice-Ramp in High-Speed Flows</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Aravinth Sadagopan, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>This is the sequel to our work on the high-fidelity analysis of the CSR geometry in hypersonic flow.  This time we reveal the key physical mechanism for shear layer oscillation, via linear stability analysis, that is the main driving force of FTSI in the case that we consider.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ee8KAvDVtUfCnroncjkL1XNbKSeixTqZ/view?usp=sharing">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2735">Evaluation of Shock Wave-Boundary Layer Interaction Modeling Capabilities for Use in a Hypersonic Aerothermoelastic Framework</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Elliot Kimmel, Daning Huang, Vansh Sharma, Jagmohan Singh, <a href="https://sites.google.com/umich.edu/apcl/home">Venkatramanan Raman</a>, <a href="https://aero.engin.umich.edu/people/friedmann-peretz-p/">Peretz P. Friedmann</a></li>
  <li>This is a major <strong>collaborative effort</strong> between Penn State and UMich.  We focus on the <strong>shock wave/boundary layer interaction</strong> over a compression ramp in hypersonic flow, and explore the key physics that may impact the structural response during the FTSI.  In short, in the case that we explored, <strong>not necessarily all</strong> complex flow features, esp. the turbulence, impact the structure.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="advanced-air-mobility">Advanced Air Mobility</h2>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2484">A Convex Approach to High-fidelity Landing Trajectory Optimization for Advanced Air Mobility</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Yufei Wu, Sabrullah Deniz, <a href="http://volweb.utk.edu/~zwang124">Zhenbo Wang</a>, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>With our collaborators from U. of Tennessee, Knoxville, we continued the previous studies that couple <strong>higher-fidelity ODE-based aerodynamic models</strong> into trajectory optimization during landing.  We develop a <strong>convexification technique</strong> to make the more complex optimization, with the ODE aero model, possible, producing more realistic trajectories for landing.  This could be leveraged for real-time deployment for <strong>safer landing</strong>.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Poster at PSU CCMA 2023</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_ccma/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Poster at PSU CCMA 2023" /><published>2023-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/ccma</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_ccma/"><![CDATA[<p>The symposium on computational mathematics for engineering and sciences, held by <a href="https://ccma.math.psu.edu/conferences-and-workshops/symposium/">CCMA</a>, took place on Nov. 13-14.  We contributed a poster on learning algorithms for dynamical systems, that achieve high accuracy with low computational cost and, most importantly, are easy to implement.  This is a combination of work from our Ph.D. students, Yin Yu and Carlos Vargas Venegas.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2311.png" width="1000" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="CarlosVV" /><category term="YinY" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The symposium on computational mathematics for engineering and sciences, held by CCMA, took place on Nov. 13-14. We contributed a poster on learning algorithms for dynamical systems, that achieve high accuracy with low computational cost and, most importantly, are easy to implement. This is a combination of work from our Ph.D. students, Yin Yu and Carlos Vargas Venegas.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">High Speed Composite Rotor Optimization</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/rsch_rotor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="High Speed Composite Rotor Optimization" /><published>2023-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/rotor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/rsch_rotor/"><![CDATA[<p>This year, we presented at the annual review meeting of VLRCOE (<a href="https://www.vlrcoe.psu.edu/">Vertical Lift Research Center of Excellence</a>) and kicked-off a new additional task on the aeroelastic optimization of high-speed composite rotor blades, with an ultimate goal to consider multiple practical factors/disciplines during the optimization.  This project is led by Dr. Edward Smith.</p>

<p>This is just a start, and more details to come in 2024!</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This year, we presented at the annual review meeting of VLRCOE (Vertical Lift Research Center of Excellence) and kicked-off a new additional task on the aeroelastic optimization of high-speed composite rotor blades, with an ultimate goal to consider multiple practical factors/disciplines during the optimization. This project is led by Dr. Edward Smith.]]></summary></entry></feed>