<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-13T16:47:45-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">APUS Lab</title><subtitle>Multi-Disciplinary Analysis, Optimization, and Control</subtitle><entry><title type="html">APUS at AIAA SciTech 2025</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_st25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APUS at AIAA SciTech 2025" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/st25</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_st25/"><![CDATA[<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2501_1.png" width="400" /></td>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2501_2.png" width="350" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>At the AIAA SciTech 2025 conference, we contributed three papers over a range of research fields, with our collaborators. Here are the summaries:</p>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2025-1017">A Parametric Study for the Effect of Morphing on Aerial Vehicles in Obstacle Avoidance</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Parker Smith and Daning Huang</li>
  <li>Though preliminary, this is the first research product from our recent <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER Award</a>.  In this paper, we studied the <strong>effects of morphing</strong> of an aerial vehicle in the scenarios of reachability and obstacle avoidance.  It was found that considering morphing in an aerial vehicle via a global coordination over the entire flight mission (via trajectory optimization) can release the full potential of morphing, and enable <strong>drastically enhanced maneuverability</strong> when compared to the fixed-wing counterpart.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1cokKH3y8t1qTtyFiDS37IZAy0z1P3zKY/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2025-0423">Global Description of Flutter Dynamics via Koopman Theory</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jiwoo Song and Daning Huang</li>
  <li>As a continuation from <a href="/news_st24/">last year’s work</a>, we developed a rigorous framework for <strong>globally linearizing</strong> nonlinear flutter dynamics using a <strong>General Koopman Bilinear Form</strong>, and show that using partial measurements of pre-flutter dynamics one can construct a dynamical model to <strong>predict the onset of flutter</strong>.  Demonstrated on a high-speed panel flutter problem.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1dusJi1-No8OSinkRYJHsJ6jqojPDr_CU/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2025-1134">Reduced-Order Modeling of Resolved Turbulent Flows for High-Speed Fluid-Structure Interaction Analysis</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Elliot Kimmel, Daning Huang, Vansh Sharma, Jagmohan Singh, <a href="https://sites.google.com/umich.edu/apcl/home">Venkatramanan Raman</a>, <a href="https://aero.engin.umich.edu/people/friedmann-peretz-p/">Peretz P. Friedmann</a></li>
  <li>This is a major <strong>collaborative effort</strong> between Penn State and UMich.  We focus on the <strong>shock wave/boundary layer interaction</strong> over a compression ramp in hypersonic flow, and this time we developed <strong>reduced-order model</strong> method capable of generating resolved turbulent boundary layer pressure fluctuation loads at a reduced computational cost for aeroelastic analysis.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Carlos Vargas Venegas for passing his Ph.D. comprehensive exam!</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/12/02/cvv-comp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Carlos Vargas Venegas for passing his Ph.D. comprehensive exam!" /><published>2024-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/12/02/cvv-comp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/12/02/cvv-comp/"><![CDATA[<p>Carlos Vargas Venegas has now came up with a comprehensive plan for his thesis: <strong>“Development of the Control-Theoretic Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling and Its Applications to Non-Linear Dynamical Systems”</strong>.  The research formed the basis of our recent <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER Award</a>.</p>

<p>Now on to the last stage of his Ph.D. life…</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="CarlosVV" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Carlos Vargas Venegas has now came up with a comprehensive plan for his thesis: “Development of the Control-Theoretic Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling and Its Applications to Non-Linear Dynamical Systems”. The research formed the basis of our recent NSF CAREER Award.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan for passing PhD defense!</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/11/22/azs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan for passing PhD defense!" /><published>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/11/22/azs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/11/22/azs/"><![CDATA[<p>On 11/22/2024, Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan successfully defended his PhD thesis, “Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of a Control Surface in Hypersonic Flow: Numerical Simulation, Experimental Correlation and Reduced-Order Modeling”.</p>

<p>Aravinth’s work represents the physics-based analysis end of our spectrum of research.  Some of his research have been summarized in <a href="/rsch_csr/">this post</a>.  More work are under preparation or under review.  Aravinth’s work was supported by <a href="/award_snl_22/">Sandia National Lab</a> and an FAA ASCENT project, as well as teaching assistantships from the department.</p>

<p>Aravinth is the second PhD student to graduate from our group.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="AravinthS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 11/22/2024, Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan successfully defended his PhD thesis, “Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of a Control Surface in Hypersonic Flow: Numerical Simulation, Experimental Correlation and Reduced-Order Modeling”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Jiwoo Song for passing his Ph.D. candidacy exam!</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/10/25/jzs-cand/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Jiwoo Song for passing his Ph.D. candidacy exam!" /><published>2024-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/10/25/jzs-cand</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/10/25/jzs-cand/"><![CDATA[<p>Jiwoo started his journey with the APUS lab as a Master’s student and graduated in April 2024, and now he has passed the qualifying exam and become an official Ph.D. student. Good job!</p>

<p>PS: Rumor says he topped the candidacy exam.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="JiwooS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jiwoo started his journey with the APUS lab as a Master’s student and graduated in April 2024, and now he has passed the qualifying exam and become an official Ph.D. student. Good job!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CAV seminar by Dr. Ashwin Renganathan from AERSP</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/10/08/renga/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CAV seminar by Dr. Ashwin Renganathan from AERSP" /><published>2024-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/10/08/renga</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/10/08/renga/"><![CDATA[<p>We hosted <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/csdl/">Dr. Ashwin Renganathan</a> from AERSP/ICDS of PSU for a <a href="https://www.cav.psu.edu/resources/seminar-archive.aspx">CAV talk</a> via the AI/ML technical group.  Dr. Renganathan is an expert in Bayesian decision theory.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract</strong>  Modern day engineering decision-making involves one or more computer simulation oracles of an engineered system which can be queried on-demand to learn the system response to control input. Querying simulation oracles, also called “computer experiments”, incur a non-trivial computational cost, which increases with the level of fidelity in the underlying models. For instance, a realistic computational aerodynamic simulation of an aircraft can cost several thousands of CPU hours to compute—anything more than a few dozens of such simulations is prohibitive. Therefore, a central goal of engineering decision-making is to optimally design computer experiments, to maximize the value of information extracted at minimal computational effort.</p>

<p>In this talk, we will address problems anchored in the decision-making triad namely: experiment design, uncertainty quantification, and numerical optimization. Specifically, using variants of Gaussian process surrogate models and a Bayesian decision theoretic framework, we will show that problems in the decision-making triad can be solved in a principled, theoretically sound and, yet, (computational) cost-effective manner. We will show demonstrations on applications in computational aerodynamics.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Seminar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We hosted Dr. Ashwin Renganathan from AERSP/ICDS of PSU for a CAV talk via the AI/ML technical group. Dr. Renganathan is an expert in Bayesian decision theory.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Yin Yu for passing PhD defense!</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/09/24/yu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Yin Yu for passing PhD defense!" /><published>2024-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/09/24/yu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/09/24/yu/"><![CDATA[<p>On 09/24/2024, Mr. Yin Yu successfully defended his PhD thesis, “Physics-Informed Data-Driven Modeling of Complex Networked Systems Through Graph Neural Networks”.</p>

<p>Yin’s work represents the data-driven end of our spectrum of research.  Some of his research have been summarized in this post: <a href="/rsch_dgn/">Geometric Deep Learning for Dynamics on Graphs</a>.  His recent work further extends to <a href="/news_wgkbf/">methodology</a>, <a href="/news_kuramoto/">theory</a>, and <a href="/news_downscale/">application</a>.  Yin’s work was supported by <a href="/award_amps_22/">the NSF AMPS program</a> and an <a href="/award_icds_22/">internal ICDS seed grant</a>, as well as teaching assistantships from the department.</p>

<p>Yin is the first PhD student to graduate from our group.  Congrats, <strong>Dr.</strong> Yu!</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="YinY" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 09/24/2024, Mr. Yin Yu successfully defended his PhD thesis, “Physics-Informed Data-Driven Modeling of Complex Networked Systems Through Graph Neural Networks”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome New Lab Member – Mr. Bayu Prasetyo</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/08/30/mbp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome New Lab Member – Mr. Bayu Prasetyo" /><published>2024-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/08/30/mbp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/08/30/mbp/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/img/head_bayu_prasetyo.png" width="400" /></p>

<p>Mr. Bayu Prasetyo graduated from Penn State in 2024 with an Honors Thesis: “Leveraging Koopman Operator Theory to Design a Drone Controller for Operation in Nonlinear Flight Conditions”.  He continued to work with us, and co-advisor <a href="https://ari-psu.github.io/">Dr. Junyi Geng</a>, on quadcopter control using Koopman dynamics.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="SubarnaP" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome New Lab Member – Mr. Subarna Pudasaini</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/08/30/sfp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome New Lab Member – Mr. Subarna Pudasaini" /><published>2024-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/08/30/sfp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2024/08/30/sfp/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/img/head_subarna_pudasaini.jpg" width="400" /></p>

<p>Mr. Subarna Pudasaini obtained a B.E. in Aerospace Engineering from Tribhuvan University (TU), Nepal, in 2023.  Now he joins Penn State with a research topic on the control co-design of morphing aerial vehicles.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="SubarnaP" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning Bilinear Dynamics of Networked Systems</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_wgkbf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Bilinear Dynamics of Networked Systems" /><published>2024-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-07-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/wgkbf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_wgkbf/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Networked systems</strong>, i.e., the systems that involve many interacting dynamical components, are universal in engineering; an example is the energy system of an electrified aircraft.  Obtaining a dynamic model from the data of such a system has two challenges: (1) the data is unstructured (defined on graph) - this causes difficulties in model representation, and (2) the system is typically stiff due to multiple timescales - this causes difficulties in learning the dynamics.</p>

<p>To overcome the above challenges, in our recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16779.pdf">ArXiv</a> manuscript, we developed a <strong>weak Latent Dynamics Model</strong> (wLDM) for learning possibly stiff nonlinear dynamics with control, and extended the wLDM framework to develop <strong>weak Graph Koopman Bilinear Form</strong> (wGKBF) model, which integrates geometric deep learning and Koopman theory to learn latent space dynamics for networked systems.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with <a href="https://www.paclab.info/">Dr. Herschel Pangborn</a> from Mechanical Engineering at Penn State.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2407_2.png" width="600" /></p>

<p>(Figure shows effectiveness of wGKBF model in comparison to the standard biDMD algorithm for an electrified aircraft system.)</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="YinY" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Networked systems, i.e., the systems that involve many interacting dynamical components, are universal in engineering; an example is the energy system of an electrified aircraft. Obtaining a dynamic model from the data of such a system has two challenges: (1) the data is unstructured (defined on graph) - this causes difficulties in model representation, and (2) the system is typically stiff due to multiple timescales - this causes difficulties in learning the dynamics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Downscaling Unstructured Spatiotemporal Data</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_downscale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Downscaling Unstructured Spatiotemporal Data" /><published>2024-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-06-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/downscale</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_downscale/"><![CDATA[<p>The <strong>resolution-coverage dilemma</strong> is a common challenge in climate research, where the coverage is inversely proportional to the resolution at the same cost.  Downscaling is a technique to overcome the dilemma by fusing spatiotemporal data of different resolutions.  Downscaling has been done for spatially continuous datasets, such as climate simulation data, but it remains a challenge to fuse unstructured distributed data, such as weather station measurements.</p>

<p>In our <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2212095524001998">recent work</a>, we tackle the downscaling involving a mixture of structured and unstructured data via a <strong>graph neural network</strong> (GNN) framework, and applied the framework to a street-level temperature estimation problem.  Furthermore, we conducted in-depth analysis of feature importance to enhance the <strong>model interpretability</strong>; sensitivity of features are shown in figure below.  Our findings highlight GNN’s high potential in capturing the complex dynamics between urban elements and their impacts on microclimate, thus offering valuable insights for comprehensive urban data collection and urban climate modeling in general.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with <a href="https://atmos.illinois.edu/directory/profile/sharmaa">Dr. Ashish Sharma</a> and Dr. Peiyuan Li from UIUC/DPI.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2406_2.jpg" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="YinY" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The resolution-coverage dilemma is a common challenge in climate research, where the coverage is inversely proportional to the resolution at the same cost. Downscaling is a technique to overcome the dilemma by fusing spatiotemporal data of different resolutions. Downscaling has been done for spatially continuous datasets, such as climate simulation data, but it remains a challenge to fuse unstructured distributed data, such as weather station measurements.]]></summary></entry></feed>