<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-15T16:04:45-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">APUS Lab</title><subtitle>Multi-Disciplinary Analysis, Optimization, and Control</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Data-driven discovery of symmetry</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_liesym/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data-driven discovery of symmetry" /><published>2025-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-11-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/liesym</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_liesym/"><![CDATA[<p>Symmetry in differential equations reveals invariances and offers a powerful means to reduce model complexity and reveal hidden physics.  However, identifying Lie symmetries directly from scattered data, without explicit knowledge of the governing equations, remains a significant challenge.  <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2511.09779">Our work</a> introduces a novel numerical scheme that can recover continuous symmetries (e.g., rotations) without requiring the analytical form of the differential equations.  Furthermore, the scheme is grounded by the theory of manifold learning and provably convergent.</p>

<p>The possible applications of the method are vast: from Hamiltonian dynamics in space to fluid and solid dynamics, or anything involving complex differential equations (ordinary, partial, with algebraic constraints, with intergals, etc.).  We are open to any potential collaborations in applying the algorithms.  The first version of the code is available <a href="https://github.com/MaxKreider/SymmetryAndScaling">here</a>.</p>

<p>This work is supported by <a href="/award_cdse_25/">NSF CDSE Program</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2511_2.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Symmetry in differential equations reveals invariances and offers a powerful means to reduce model complexity and reveal hidden physics. However, identifying Lie symmetries directly from scattered data, without explicit knowledge of the governing equations, remains a significant challenge. Our work introduces a novel numerical scheme that can recover continuous symmetries (e.g., rotations) without requiring the analytical form of the differential equations. Furthermore, the scheme is grounded by the theory of manifold learning and provably convergent.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Huang delivered a research seminar at RPI</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2025/10/01/rpi-sem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Huang delivered a research seminar at RPI" /><published>2025-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2025/10/01/rpi-sem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news/2025/10/01/rpi-sem/"><![CDATA[<p>On Oct. 1st, Dr. Huang delivered a seminar in <a href="mane.rpi.edu/">Department of Mechanical, Aerospace, and Nuclear Engineering at Rensselear Polytechnic Institute</a>.  The seminar is invited by Prof. <a href="www.shaowupan.com/">Shaowu Pan at RPI</a>.  The seminar presents some of the key achievements of the group in the past years, esp. <strong>Impossible Trinity of Modeling</strong>, and some of the current main research thrusts.</p>

<p>It was a fun visit.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Seminar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Oct. 1st, Dr. Huang delivered a seminar in Department of Mechanical, Aerospace, and Nuclear Engineering at Rensselear Polytechnic Institute. The seminar is invited by Prof. Shaowu Pan at RPI. The seminar presents some of the key achievements of the group in the past years, esp. Impossible Trinity of Modeling, and some of the current main research thrusts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CDS&amp;amp;E project awarded from NSF</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/award_cdse_25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CDS&amp;amp;E project awarded from NSF" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/cdse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/award_cdse_25/"><![CDATA[<p>We are happy to announce the award of an <a href="www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2505605">NSF project</a> from the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/cdse-computational-data-enabled-science-engineering">Computational and Data-Enabled Science and Engineering (CDS&amp;E)</a> program, titled <strong>Leveraging Geometric Structure in Learning Dynamical Systems</strong>.  The project is joint with <a href="https://jharlim.github.io/myhomepage/">Prof. John Harlim</a> from Penn State Math.</p>

<p>The goal of the project is to reveal geometric structures encoded in the measured time series of the dynamics, i.e., the data manifold, to enable compact reduced-order modeling for scalable numerical simulations.  Specifically, we will consider (1) learning dynamics on manifolds with provable preservation of geometrical constraints; (2) learning Lie symmetry groups of dynamics, that leads to scaling/similarity laws of complex dynamical systems.</p>

<p>The first aim generalizes our physics-infused reduced-order modeling (ROM) methodology from the <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER project</a> into a <strong>geometry-infused</strong> ROM.  The second aim is a leap from our prior work on aerothermoelastic scaling (brutal force in engineering) to a more systematic and elegant mathematical treatment via Lie group theory.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are happy to announce the award of an NSF project from the Computational and Data-Enabled Science and Engineering (CDS&amp;E) program, titled Leveraging Geometric Structure in Learning Dynamical Systems. The project is joint with Prof. John Harlim from Penn State Math.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Python package published - DyMAD</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_dymad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Python package published - DyMAD" /><published>2025-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/dymad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_dymad/"><![CDATA[<p>We have published the first software package from our lab, DyMAD.  See <a href="https://github.com/apus-lab/dymad">Code</a> and <a href="https://dymad.readthedocs.io/">Documentation</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Feel free to try it out, give feedback, and/or contribute!</strong></p>

<p>DyMAD aims to provide a lightweight and user-friendly toolkit for modeling and analyzing dynamical systems using data-driven approaches.</p>

<p>Currently, we have implemented the following features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Data preprocessing pipeline specialized for time series data.</li>
  <li>Models for different types of dynamical systems, including
    <ul>
      <li>Latent Dynamics Models</li>
      <li>Koopman Bilinear Forms</li>
      <li>The graph version of the above</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Training utilities, including
    <ul>
      <li>Neural-ODE-based optimizer</li>
      <li>Weak-form optimizer</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Miscellaneous utilities, including
    <ul>
      <li>Samplers for inputs and initial conditions</li>
      <li>Visualization tools</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The implemented and planned algorithms and features for DyMAD are mainly based on the <a href="/publications/">research work</a> from our lab.  The lead developer is Dr. Yin Yu, whose PhD thesis is on the topic of data-driven modeling of dynamical systems on graphs.</p>

<p>It is still far from complete, see our <a href="https://dymad.readthedocs.io/en/latest/roadmap.html">Roadmap</a> for more details.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="Software" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have published the first software package from our lab, DyMAD. See Code and Documentation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning Coarse-Grained Dynamics on Graph - now on Physica D</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_physd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Coarse-Grained Dynamics on Graph - now on Physica D" /><published>2025-06-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-06-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/physd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_physd/"><![CDATA[<p>Our <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.09324">ArXiv</a> paper from last year (see previous post and summary <a href="/news_kuramoto/">here</a>) has been published in <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167278925002787">Physica D: Nonlinear Phenomena</a>.</p>

<p>Compared to our initial version, we refined the theoretical derivation as well as the explanation of examples.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="YinY" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our ArXiv paper from last year (see previous post and summary here) has been published in Physica D: Nonlinear Phenomena.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_pirom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling" /><published>2025-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-06-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/pirom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_pirom/"><![CDATA[<p>The tackling of the <a href="/research/#impossible-trinity-of-modeling">Impossible Trinity of Modeling</a> has been one of the research themes of our group, that is central to our efforts in the multi-disciplinary optimization of dynamical systems.</p>

<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.22890">Our recent work</a> is a milestone of such effort.  We developed a systematic reduced-order modeling methodology that integrates the coarse-graining theory from statistical mechanics and numerical methods from machine learning community.  The end product is the <strong>physics-infused reduced-order modeling</strong> (PIROM), that is simultaneously <strong>accurate</strong>, <strong>computationally efficient</strong>, and <strong>extrapolates to unseen scenarios</strong>.  In conventional modeling, achieving any of the two sacrifices the third.</p>

<p>We demonstrated the methodology on a high-speed thermal protection system, governed by a parameterized nonlinear parabolic PDE.  While the PIROM is trained using only one set of material properties, it achieves <strong>zero-shot learning</strong> and extrapolates with ease to completely new material properties without any new samples.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with collaborators from the Sandia National Lab, Drs. Patrick Blonigan and John Tencer.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2506_1.png" width="600" /> <img src="/img/post_2506_2.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="CarlosVV" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The tackling of the Impossible Trinity of Modeling has been one of the research themes of our group, that is central to our efforts in the multi-disciplinary optimization of dynamical systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Global linear representation of flutter dynamics</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_koopman/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global linear representation of flutter dynamics" /><published>2025-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-05-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/koop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_koopman/"><![CDATA[<p>The Koopman theory is now a well-known tool in the analysis of nonlinear dynamics.  <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.14697">Our work</a> looks into how Koopman theory, particularly the <strong>Koopman Bilinear Form</strong> (KBF) and its extension (EKBF), can be leveraged in the <strong>global linear representation</strong> of aeroelastic dynamics, including <strong>Hopf bifurcation</strong> with flutter behaviors.</p>

<p>The effectiveness of the proposed methodology is demonstrated through two case studies: a 2D academic example and a panel flutter problem. Results show that EKBF effectively interpolates and extrapolates principal eigenvalues, capturing flutter mechanisms, and accurately predicting the flutter boundary even when the data is corrupted by noise. Furthermore, parameterized isostable and isochron identified by EKBF provides valuable insights into the nonlinear flutter system.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2505_3.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="JiwooS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Koopman theory is now a well-known tool in the analysis of nonlinear dynamics. Our work looks into how Koopman theory, particularly the Koopman Bilinear Form (KBF) and its extension (EKBF), can be leveraged in the global linear representation of aeroelastic dynamics, including Hopf bifurcation with flutter behaviors.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APUS at VFS 2025</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_vfs25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APUS at VFS 2025" /><published>2025-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/vfs25</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_vfs25/"><![CDATA[<p>At the recent Vertical Flight Society’s 81st Annual Forum (VFS81), we presented our work on the optimization of rotor blade structures, supported by a <a href="/rsch_rotor/">VLRCOE</a> task.  Aiming to expand the existing capabilities and practices in rotor blade optimization, we explore how manufacturability of the composite struture may be incorporated into the optimization problem.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with <a href="https://www.aero.psu.edu/department/directory-detail-g.aspx?q=ECS5">Dr. Edward Smith</a> from Aerospace and Dr. R. B. Haehnel from Army ERDC.</p>

<p>For more details, see <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Q2D36HL2x0ud-hl_yyeI-_zsiIivgdL5/view?usp=sharing">paper</a>, <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1PyLkDbk6p5tIls1kU4bmNMNn-j4duMqy/view?usp=sharing">slides</a>, and an earlier version of <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1J84G8ZCidcfeh42pmJKcw1cP_AjKnWld/view?usp=sharing">poster</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2505_2.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="JiwooS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the recent Vertical Flight Society’s 81st Annual Forum (VFS81), we presented our work on the optimization of rotor blade structures, supported by a VLRCOE task. Aiming to expand the existing capabilities and practices in rotor blade optimization, we explore how manufacturability of the composite struture may be incorporated into the optimization problem.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APUS at SSDM 2025</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_ssdm25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APUS at SSDM 2025" /><published>2025-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/ssdm25</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_ssdm25/"><![CDATA[<p>At the recent ASME Aerospace Structures, Structural Dynamics, and Materials Conference (SSDM) 2025 conference, we presented our on-going work towards the control co-design of morphing aerial vehicles, supported by our <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER Award</a>.</p>

<p>In this presentation, we focused on the mid-fidelity <strong>aeroservoelastic modeling</strong>, as well as the <strong>trajectory optimization</strong> (TO) based on this model.  In particular, we explored sampling-based algorithms to solve the aeroservoelastic TO problem, which would have been computationally intractable if the standard gradient-based algorithms were used.</p>

<p>For more details, see <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1oOUymyuyDU5_UdI7j2ciux3bj_c1n2fc/view?usp=sharing">paper</a> and <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1pTYArFJxk8w30zgWWx34lSf6D3OiRhRt/view?usp=sharing">slides</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="SubarnaP" /><category term="ParkerS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the recent ASME Aerospace Structures, Structural Dynamics, and Materials Conference (SSDM) 2025 conference, we presented our on-going work towards the control co-design of morphing aerial vehicles, supported by our NSF CAREER Award.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spotlight paper at ICLR 2025</title><link href="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_iclr25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spotlight paper at ICLR 2025" /><published>2025-03-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-03-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://apus-lab.github.io/iclr25</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://apus-lab.github.io/news_iclr25/"><![CDATA[<p>For the coming ICLR 2025 conference we are proud to present a <strong>Spotlight paper</strong>: “Learning vector fields of differential equations on manifolds with geometrically constrained operator-valued kernels”.  Only 3.3% papers of the nearly 11500 submissions are selected as Spotlight.</p>

<p>In this work, we address the problem of learning ordinary differential equations (ODEs) on manifolds by devising (1) an <strong>operator-valued kernel</strong> to represent vector fields on manifolds and (2) a <strong>geometry-preserving time integrator</strong> that enforces the ODE solution to lie a manifold.  The algorithm is rooted in theories of differential goemetry and dynamical systems, with <strong>rigorous convergence bounds</strong>.  We verify the effectiveness of the proposed approach on high-dimensional dynamical systems, including the cavity flow problem, the beating and travelling waves in Kuramoto-Sivashinsky equations, and the reaction-diffusion dynamics.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with <a href="https://jharlim.github.io/myhomepage/">Dr. John Harlim</a> from Math &amp; Meteorology and <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/yanli/">Dr. Yan Li</a> from EECS at Penn State.</p>

<p>For more details, see <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=OwpLQrpdwE">paper and code</a>, <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1jFpbzndik1TFbNGC7OJ4TACv-LBlqFY1/view?usp=drive_link">slides</a>, <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1lIsmysqS0V37N3xpXopSNhCPhnDHS7oo/view?usp=sharing">poster</a>, and <a href="https://recorder-v3.slideslive.com/?share=99288&amp;s=65a0c8b3-fc77-4350-bb8b-bf8def8340a3">5-min presentation</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2503_4.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the coming ICLR 2025 conference we are proud to present a Spotlight paper: “Learning vector fields of differential equations on manifolds with geometrically constrained operator-valued kernels”. Only 3.3% papers of the nearly 11500 submissions are selected as Spotlight.]]></summary></entry></feed>