<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-25T17:28:57-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">APUS Lab</title><subtitle>Multi-Disciplinary Analysis, Optimization, and Control</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Going to ICLR 2025</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_iclr25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Going to ICLR 2025" /><published>2025-03-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-03-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/iclr25</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_iclr25/"><![CDATA[<p>For the coming ICLR 2025 conference we are proud to present a <strong>Spotlight paper</strong>: “Learning vector fields of differential equations on manifolds with geometrically constrained operator-valued kernels”.  Only 3.3% papers of the nearly 11500 submissions are selected as Spotlight.</p>

<p>In this work, we address the problem of learning ordinary differential equations (ODEs) on manifolds by devising (1) an <strong>operator-valued kernel</strong> to represent vector fields on manifolds and (2) a <strong>geometry-preserving time integrator</strong> that enforces the ODE solution to lie a manifold.  The algorithm is rooted in theories of differential goemetry and dynamical systems, with <strong>rigorous convergence bounds</strong>.  We verify the effectiveness of the proposed approach on high-dimensional dynamical systems, including the cavity flow problem, the beating and travelling waves in Kuramoto-Sivashinsky equations, and the reaction-diffusion dynamics.</p>

<p>The work is done jointly with <a href="https://jharlim.github.io/myhomepage/">Dr. John Harlim</a> from Math &amp; Meteorology and <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/yanli/">Dr. Yan Li</a> from EECS at Penn State.</p>

<p>For more details, see <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=OwpLQrpdwE">paper and code</a>, <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1jFpbzndik1TFbNGC7OJ4TACv-LBlqFY1/view?usp=drive_link">slides</a>, <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1lIsmysqS0V37N3xpXopSNhCPhnDHS7oo/view?usp=sharing">poster</a>, and <a href="https://recorder-v3.slideslive.com/?share=99288&amp;s=65a0c8b3-fc77-4350-bb8b-bf8def8340a3">5-min presentation</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2503_4.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the coming ICLR 2025 conference we are proud to present a Spotlight paper: “Learning vector fields of differential equations on manifolds with geometrically constrained operator-valued kernels”. Only 3.3% papers of the nearly 11500 submissions are selected as Spotlight.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Huang delivered a research seminar in the department</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2025/03/20/dept-sem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Huang delivered a research seminar in the department" /><published>2025-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2025/03/20/dept-sem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2025/03/20/dept-sem/"><![CDATA[<p>On Mar. 20th, Dr. Huang delivered a seminar in the department, since his last seminar in 2019.  The seminar presents some of the key achievements of the group in the past years, and some of the current main research thrusts.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract</strong>: This talk addresses the challenges in designing the next-generation engineering systems — think high-speed aircraft and autonomous vehicles — which require a control co-design approach that considers dynamical and control performance at an early design stage.  In this case, the co-design suffers from a computational bottleneck, denoted as the <strong>Impossible Trinity of Modeling</strong>.  This means, for a dynamical model, satisfying any two sacrifices the third: high fidelity, computational efficiency, and design parametrization.</p>

<p>We present our recent efforts in resolving the bottleneck via the <strong>Geometry-Informed Reduced-Order Modeling</strong>.  In simple terms, we use known physical laws and the inherent topology of the system dynamics to build data-driven models that turn the Impossible Trinity to a possible one.  This methodology potentially opens up the path towards integrated multi-disciplinary optimization of complex dynamical systems.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Seminar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Mar. 20th, Dr. Huang delivered a seminar in the department, since his last seminar in 2019. The seminar presents some of the key achievements of the group in the past years, and some of the current main research thrusts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APUS at SIAM CSE25</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_cse25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APUS at SIAM CSE25" /><published>2025-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-03-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cse25</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_cse25/"><![CDATA[<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2405_2.png" width="400" /></td>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2503_1.png" width="400" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>At the 2025 SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering, we contributed two talks with our collaborators. Here are the summaries:</p>

<p><a href="https://meetings.siam.org/sess/dsp_talk.cfm?p=140761">Learning Coarse-Grained Dynamics on Graphs</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Yin Yu, <a href="https://jharlim.github.io/myhomepage/">John Harlim</a>, Daning Huang, and <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/yanli/">Yan Li</a></li>
  <li>This is the presentation of our <a href="/news_kuramoto/">earlier paper</a> (ArXiv version <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09324.pdf">here</a>).  We systematically developed <strong>coarse-grained reduced-order models</strong> for networked dynamical systems.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1RW1lehuAhdtzmp_qqxyYABBPe7g5LaLu/view?usp=sharing">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://meetings.siam.org/sess/dsp_talk.cfm?p=142321">Towards Control Co-design of Morphing Aerial Autonomous Systems by Multi-objective Optimization</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Parker Smith, Subarna Pudasaini, and Daning Huang</li>
  <li>This is an on-going work supported by our <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER Award</a>.  In this paper, we attempted to <strong>formulate a control co-design problem</strong> while bypassing the expensive solves of trajectory optimization sub-problems.  In an initial demonstration, the new formulation is extremely fast to solve and the results align with physical intuition.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1WN06pK573sxPjnCM9yXoqdNdByobvVR7/view?usp=sharing">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="YinY" /><category term="SubarnaP" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AIAAJ - Modal Analysis via Multivariate Gaussian Process Regression</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_mvgprj/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AIAAJ - Modal Analysis via Multivariate Gaussian Process Regression" /><published>2025-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mvgpr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_mvgprj/"><![CDATA[<p>Our ArXiv manuscript has just been published on <a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/1.J064185">AIAAJ</a>, led by our lab member, Jiwoo Song.  This is an innovative application of multi-variate Gaussian process regression to the modal analysis of spatiotemporal data, such as unsteady flow fields.  Our method is particularly suitable for the cases where the data set is scarce and/or the temporal sampling is irregular; in these cases, the conventional methods such as spectral proper orthogonal decomposition do not work well.  This is one of our efforts in one of our core thrusts, <a href="/rsch_std/">Scientific Data Analysis</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2403_2.png" width="600" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><category term="JiwooS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our ArXiv manuscript has just been published on AIAAJ, led by our lab member, Jiwoo Song. This is an innovative application of multi-variate Gaussian process regression to the modal analysis of spatiotemporal data, such as unsteady flow fields. Our method is particularly suitable for the cases where the data set is scarce and/or the temporal sampling is irregular; in these cases, the conventional methods such as spectral proper orthogonal decomposition do not work well. This is one of our efforts in one of our core thrusts, Scientific Data Analysis.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APUS at AIAA SciTech 2025</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_st25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APUS at AIAA SciTech 2025" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/st25</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_st25/"><![CDATA[<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2501_1.png" width="400" /></td>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2501_2.png" width="350" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>At the AIAA SciTech 2025 conference, we contributed three papers over a range of research fields, with our collaborators. Here are the summaries:</p>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2025-1017">A Parametric Study for the Effect of Morphing on Aerial Vehicles in Obstacle Avoidance</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Parker Smith and Daning Huang</li>
  <li>Though preliminary, this is the first research product from our recent <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER Award</a>.  In this paper, we studied the <strong>effects of morphing</strong> of an aerial vehicle in the scenarios of reachability and obstacle avoidance.  It was found that considering morphing in an aerial vehicle via a global coordination over the entire flight mission (via trajectory optimization) can release the full potential of morphing, and enable <strong>drastically enhanced maneuverability</strong> when compared to the fixed-wing counterpart.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1cokKH3y8t1qTtyFiDS37IZAy0z1P3zKY/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2025-0423">Global Description of Flutter Dynamics via Koopman Theory</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jiwoo Song and Daning Huang</li>
  <li>As a continuation from <a href="/news_st24/">last year’s work</a>, we developed a rigorous framework for <strong>globally linearizing</strong> nonlinear flutter dynamics using a <strong>General Koopman Bilinear Form</strong>, and show that using partial measurements of pre-flutter dynamics one can construct a dynamical model to <strong>predict the onset of flutter</strong>.  Demonstrated on a high-speed panel flutter problem.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1dusJi1-No8OSinkRYJHsJ6jqojPDr_CU/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2025-1134">Reduced-Order Modeling of Resolved Turbulent Flows for High-Speed Fluid-Structure Interaction Analysis</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Elliot Kimmel, Daning Huang, Vansh Sharma, Jagmohan Singh, <a href="https://sites.google.com/umich.edu/apcl/home">Venkatramanan Raman</a>, <a href="https://aero.engin.umich.edu/people/friedmann-peretz-p/">Peretz P. Friedmann</a></li>
  <li>This is a major <strong>collaborative effort</strong> between Penn State and UMich.  We focus on the <strong>shock wave/boundary layer interaction</strong> over a compression ramp in hypersonic flow, and this time we developed <strong>reduced-order model</strong> method capable of generating resolved turbulent boundary layer pressure fluctuation loads at a reduced computational cost for aeroelastic analysis.</li>
</ul>

<p>Lastly, Dr. Huang was able to contribute to the Education Outreach event organized by the AIAA Structural Dynamics TC at the Walker Middle School.  The teachers at the school were so kind and made a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GIMSsdpuNN8">video</a> for the event.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Carlos Vargas Venegas for passing his Ph.D. comprehensive exam!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/12/02/cvv-comp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Carlos Vargas Venegas for passing his Ph.D. comprehensive exam!" /><published>2024-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2024/12/02/cvv-comp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/12/02/cvv-comp/"><![CDATA[<p>Carlos Vargas Venegas has now came up with a comprehensive plan for his thesis: <strong>“Development of the Control-Theoretic Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling and Its Applications to Non-Linear Dynamical Systems”</strong>.  The research formed the basis of our recent <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER Award</a>.</p>

<p>Now on to the last stage of his Ph.D. life…</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="CarlosVV" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Carlos Vargas Venegas has now came up with a comprehensive plan for his thesis: “Development of the Control-Theoretic Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling and Its Applications to Non-Linear Dynamical Systems”. The research formed the basis of our recent NSF CAREER Award.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan for passing PhD defense!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/11/22/azs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan for passing PhD defense!" /><published>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2024/11/22/azs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/11/22/azs/"><![CDATA[<p>On 11/22/2024, Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan successfully defended his PhD thesis, “Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of a Control Surface in Hypersonic Flow: Numerical Simulation, Experimental Correlation and Reduced-Order Modeling”.</p>

<p>Aravinth’s work represents the physics-based analysis end of our spectrum of research.  Some of his research have been summarized in <a href="/rsch_csr/">this post</a>.  More work are under preparation or under review.  Aravinth’s work was supported by <a href="/award_snl_22/">Sandia National Lab</a> and an FAA ASCENT project, as well as teaching assistantships from the department.</p>

<p>Aravinth is the second PhD student to graduate from our group.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="AravinthS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 11/22/2024, Mr. Aravinth Sadagopan successfully defended his PhD thesis, “Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of a Control Surface in Hypersonic Flow: Numerical Simulation, Experimental Correlation and Reduced-Order Modeling”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Mr. Jiwoo Song for passing his Ph.D. candidacy exam!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/10/25/jzs-cand/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Mr. Jiwoo Song for passing his Ph.D. candidacy exam!" /><published>2024-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2024/10/25/jzs-cand</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/10/25/jzs-cand/"><![CDATA[<p>Jiwoo started his journey with the APUS lab as a Master’s student and graduated in April 2024, and now he has passed the qualifying exam and become an official Ph.D. student. Good job!</p>

<p>PS: Rumor says he topped the candidacy exam.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Student" /><category term="JiwooS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jiwoo started his journey with the APUS lab as a Master’s student and graduated in April 2024, and now he has passed the qualifying exam and become an official Ph.D. student. Good job!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CAV seminar by Dr. Ashwin Renganathan from AERSP</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/10/08/renga/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CAV seminar by Dr. Ashwin Renganathan from AERSP" /><published>2024-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2024/10/08/renga</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2024/10/08/renga/"><![CDATA[<p>We hosted <a href="https://sites.psu.edu/csdl/">Dr. Ashwin Renganathan</a> from AERSP/ICDS of PSU for a <a href="https://www.cav.psu.edu/resources/seminar-archive.aspx">CAV talk</a> via the AI/ML technical group.  Dr. Renganathan is an expert in Bayesian decision theory.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract</strong>  Modern day engineering decision-making involves one or more computer simulation oracles of an engineered system which can be queried on-demand to learn the system response to control input. Querying simulation oracles, also called “computer experiments”, incur a non-trivial computational cost, which increases with the level of fidelity in the underlying models. For instance, a realistic computational aerodynamic simulation of an aircraft can cost several thousands of CPU hours to compute—anything more than a few dozens of such simulations is prohibitive. Therefore, a central goal of engineering decision-making is to optimally design computer experiments, to maximize the value of information extracted at minimal computational effort.</p>

<p>In this talk, we will address problems anchored in the decision-making triad namely: experiment design, uncertainty quantification, and numerical optimization. Specifically, using variants of Gaussian process surrogate models and a Bayesian decision theoretic framework, we will show that problems in the decision-making triad can be solved in a principled, theoretically sound and, yet, (computational) cost-effective manner. We will show demonstrations on applications in computational aerodynamics.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Seminar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We hosted Dr. Ashwin Renganathan from AERSP/ICDS of PSU for a CAV talk via the AI/ML technical group. Dr. Renganathan is an expert in Bayesian decision theory.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">STTR project awarded from Navy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/award_sttr_24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="STTR project awarded from Navy" /><published>2024-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sttr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/award_sttr_24/"><![CDATA[<p>Together with <a href="https://www.systemstech.com/">STI</a>, we are awarded a Navy STTR Phase I project, “Real-Time In-Flight Aircraft State Estimation”, that aims to enhance the capability to estimate the states and parameters of an aerial system in-flight using a data-augmented state estimation algorithm.  This is a spin-off from our physics-infused reduced-order modeling methodology from the <a href="/award_career/">NSF CAREER project</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Together with STI, we are awarded a Navy STTR Phase I project, “Real-Time In-Flight Aircraft State Estimation”, that aims to enhance the capability to estimate the states and parameters of an aerial system in-flight using a data-augmented state estimation algorithm. This is a spin-off from our physics-infused reduced-order modeling methodology from the NSF CAREER project.]]></summary></entry></feed>