<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-25T17:14:05-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">APUS Lab</title><subtitle>Multi-Disciplinary Analysis, Optimization, and Control</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Contributing to SIAM UQ24</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_uq24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Contributing to SIAM UQ24" /><published>2024-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/uq24</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_uq24/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.siam.org/conferences/cm/conference/uq24">SIAM UQ24</a> occurs in Trieste, Italy.  While we could not be physically present there, we contribute a talk on physics-infused reduced-order modeling as part of a <a href="https://meetings.siam.org/sess/dsp_programsess.cfm?SESSIONCODE=78427">minisymposium</a>: “Recent Advances in Surrogate Modeling for UQ of Large-Scale Simulations”.</p>

<p>The central idea is that, conventional surrogates for UQ of dynamical systems only support a limited number of parameters, while we aim to leverage the PIROM methodology to build surrogates that are of <strong>infinite-dimensional</strong> parameters by directly encoding known dynamics into the model.  We connect this idea to the well-known Mori-Zwanzig formalism, and present two algorithms for learning PIROMs from data, that build on our lab member Carlos’ <a href="/rsch_pirom/">previous work</a>.</p>

<p>The slides are available <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1x7qbTt-A1IDZoZ3aJA57IObquPqfnu1T/view?usp=sharing">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The SIAM UQ24 occurs in Trieste, Italy. While we could not be physically present there, we contribute a talk on physics-infused reduced-order modeling as part of a minisymposium: “Recent Advances in Surrogate Modeling for UQ of Large-Scale Simulations”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">APUS at AIAA SciTech 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_st24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="APUS at AIAA SciTech 2024" /><published>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/st24</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_st24/"><![CDATA[<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/img/post_2401_1.png" width="600" /></td>
      <td><br /><br /><img src="/img/post_2401_2.png" width="450" /></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>At the AIAA SciTech 2024 conference, we contributed six papers over a range of research fields, with our collaborators. Here are the summaries:</p>

<h2 id="operator-theoretic-methods-for-reduced-order-modeling">Operator-Theoretic Methods for Reduced-Order Modeling</h2>

<p>Dr. Huang and <a href="https://research.cec.sc.edu/wang">Dr. Yi Wang</a> co-organized a special session “Operator-Theoretic Methods for Reduced-Order Modeling in Structural Dynamics and Aeroelasticity” that focuses on the application of Koopman theory to nonlinear structural dynamics and aeroelasticity.  In this session, we contributed two papers:</p>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2266">Parametrized Global Linearization Models for Flutter Prediction</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jiwoo Song, Yin Yu, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>We provided an initial development of a rigorous framework for <strong>globally linearizing</strong> nonlinear flutter dynamics using the so-called <strong>Koopman Bilinear Form</strong>, and show that using partial measurements of pre-flutter dynamics one can construct a dynamical model, bilinear in system parameter, to <strong>predict the onset of flutter</strong>.  Demonstrated on a high-speed panel flutter problem.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/19v7fb7BjNnT6Pa9lzGaapFknpGgE2mDK/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2264">Residual Dynamic Mode Decomposition with Control for Nonlinear Aeroservoelastic Applications</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jacob C. Rains, Daning Huang, <a href="https://research.cec.sc.edu/wang">Yi Wang</a></li>
  <li>In parallel to the parametric model above, we also explore <strong>flutter dynamics with bilinear inputs</strong>, aiming to produce a unified, relatively simple yet accurate model for the <strong>flutter suppression</strong> in a wide range of flow conditions.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="physics-infused-reduced-order-modeling">Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling</h2>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-0782">Development of Weak-Form Physics-Infused Reduced-Order Modeling With Applications</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Carlos Vargas Venegas, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>We continue to work on the PIROM, in an attempt to resolve the <a href="/rsch_pirom/"><strong>Impossible Trinity of Modeling</strong></a>.  The PIROM requires learning a differential equation from data, which can pose numerical challenge in training.  We proposed and demonstrated a weak-form formulation for <strong>accelerated learning</strong> of such models.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1KOTkdKiVIMmWndtTGZCfozqEhbprfZhv/view?usp=drive_link">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="high-speed-fluid-thermal-structural-interaction">High-Speed Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction</h2>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-1050">Reduced-Order Modeling for Fluid-Thermal-Structural Interaction of Cone-Slice-Ramp in High-Speed Flows</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Aravinth Sadagopan, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>This is the sequel to our work on the high-fidelity analysis of the CSR geometry in hypersonic flow.  This time we reveal the key physical mechanism for shear layer oscillation, via linear stability analysis, that is the main driving force of FTSI in the case that we consider.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ee8KAvDVtUfCnroncjkL1XNbKSeixTqZ/view?usp=sharing">Here</a> are the slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2735">Evaluation of Shock Wave-Boundary Layer Interaction Modeling Capabilities for Use in a Hypersonic Aerothermoelastic Framework</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Elliot Kimmel, Daning Huang, Vansh Sharma, Jagmohan Singh, <a href="https://sites.google.com/umich.edu/apcl/home">Venkatramanan Raman</a>, <a href="https://aero.engin.umich.edu/people/friedmann-peretz-p/">Peretz P. Friedmann</a></li>
  <li>This is a major <strong>collaborative effort</strong> between Penn State and UMich.  We focus on the <strong>shock wave/boundary layer interaction</strong> over a compression ramp in hypersonic flow, and explore the key physics that may impact the structural response during the FTSI.  In short, in the case that we explored, <strong>not necessarily all</strong> complex flow features, esp. the turbulence, impact the structure.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="advanced-air-mobility">Advanced Air Mobility</h2>

<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/10.2514/6.2024-2484">A Convex Approach to High-fidelity Landing Trajectory Optimization for Advanced Air Mobility</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Yufei Wu, Sabrullah Deniz, <a href="http://volweb.utk.edu/~zwang124">Zhenbo Wang</a>, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>With our collaborators from U. of Tennessee, Knoxville, we continued the previous studies that couple <strong>higher-fidelity ODE-based aerodynamic models</strong> into trajectory optimization during landing.  We develop a <strong>convexification technique</strong> to make the more complex optimization, with the ODE aero model, possible, producing more realistic trajectories for landing.  This could be leveraged for real-time deployment for <strong>safer landing</strong>.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Poster at PSU CCMA 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_ccma/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Poster at PSU CCMA 2023" /><published>2023-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ccma</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_ccma/"><![CDATA[<p>The symposium on computational mathematics for engineering and sciences, held by <a href="https://ccma.math.psu.edu/conferences-and-workshops/symposium/">CCMA</a>, took place on Nov. 13-14.  We contributed a poster on learning algorithms for dynamical systems, that achieve high accuracy with low computational cost and, most importantly, are easy to implement.  This is a combination of work from our Ph.D. students, Yin Yu and Carlos Vargas Venegas.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2311.png" width="1000" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The symposium on computational mathematics for engineering and sciences, held by CCMA, took place on Nov. 13-14. We contributed a poster on learning algorithms for dynamical systems, that achieve high accuracy with low computational cost and, most importantly, are easy to implement. This is a combination of work from our Ph.D. students, Yin Yu and Carlos Vargas Venegas.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">High Speed Composite Rotor Optimization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/rsch_rotor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="High Speed Composite Rotor Optimization" /><published>2023-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/rotor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/rsch_rotor/"><![CDATA[<p>This year, we presented at the annual review meeting of VLRCOE (<a href="https://www.vlrcoe.psu.edu/">Vertical Lift Research Center of Excellence</a>) and kicked-off a new additional task on the aeroelastic optimization of high-speed composite rotor blades, with an ultimate goal to consider multiple practical factors/disciplines during the optimization.  This project is led by Dr. Edward Smith.</p>

<p>This is just a start, and more details to come in 2024!</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Funding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This year, we presented at the annual review meeting of VLRCOE (Vertical Lift Research Center of Excellence) and kicked-off a new additional task on the aeroelastic optimization of high-speed composite rotor blades, with an ultimate goal to consider multiple practical factors/disciplines during the optimization. This project is led by Dr. Edward Smith.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CAV seminar by Dr. Romit Maulik from IST</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2023/10/18/maulik/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CAV seminar by Dr. Romit Maulik from IST" /><published>2023-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2023/10/18/maulik</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2023/10/18/maulik/"><![CDATA[<p>We hosted <a href="https://romit-maulik.github.io/">Dr. Romit Maulik</a> from IST/ICDS of PSU for a <a href="https://www.cav.psu.edu/resources/seminar-archive.aspx">CAV talk</a> via the AI/ML technical group.  Dr. Maulik is an expert in scientific machine learning.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract</strong>  The talk gives a high-level overview of several projects underway at the Interdisciplinary Scientific Computing Laboratory (ISCL) at Pennsylvania State University. ISCL is housed in the School of Information Science and Technology and performs research in scientific machine learning (SciML) with applications to various domain sciences. Our research program sits at the intersection of machine learning, high-performance computing, and computational science and engineering while being motivated by grand challenge problems in different domains. Some of the research areas investigated in ISCL include novel methods for physics-informed surrogate modeling, multimodal data and model fusion, interpretable machine learning for scientific computing, and scientific reinforcement learning for controlling simulations. Furthermore, ISCL is also devoted to the development of scalable and reproducible methods for machine learning that may interface with legacy computing workflows. The presented talk will be free-form and interactive, with the speaker taking requests from the audience for deep-dives into specific research themes to enable future collaborations.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Seminar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We hosted Dr. Romit Maulik from IST/ICDS of PSU for a CAV talk via the AI/ML technical group. Dr. Maulik is an expert in scientific machine learning.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Department seminar by Dr. Sicheng He from UTK</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2023/07/27/he/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Department seminar by Dr. Sicheng He from UTK" /><published>2023-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2023/07/27/he</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2023/07/27/he/"><![CDATA[<p>We hosted Dr. <a href="https://sichenghe.github.io/">Sicheng He</a> from University of Tennessee, Knoxville, for a seminar in our department.  Dr. He’s expertise lies in the high-fidelity optimization of multi-disciplinary dynamical systems.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract</strong> Multidisciplinary design optimization (MDO) has been widely used in the aerospace industry. Problems with millions of state variables and hundreds of design variables are solved. However, from the perspective of dynamical systems, most of the previous research focused on equilibrium point problems. To enable MDO for general dynamical systems, we develop efficient computation methods based on Jacobian-free Newton-Krylov (JFNK), algorithmic differentiation (AD), and adjoint methods. Applications in wind turbine design and aeroelastic limit cycle oscillation (LCO) (or flutter) suppression are discussed. Besides, control co-design (CCD) is an emerging field that aims to incorporate optimal control as one discipline into MDO to substitute the traditional sequential design workflow used in the industry. CCD is a powerful idea that can exploit the complex interaction between the plant and the control variables. However, most of the previous research focused on low-fidelity models. To enable CCD for high-fidelity models, we propose an efficient sensitivity computation method based on the coupled adjoint method. A quadrotor blade CCD problem is presented where the control cost is reduced by about 50% from a sequentially optimized design. Finally, we discuss the data-driven method in aerodynamic shape optimization. Using our neural network model, we can conduct real-time airfoil shape optimization with accurate lift, drag, and moment coefficients (&lt;1% relative error) for both subsonic and transonic regimes.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Seminar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We hosted Dr. Sicheng He from University of Tennessee, Knoxville, for a seminar in our department. Dr. He’s expertise lies in the high-fidelity optimization of multi-disciplinary dynamical systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PyPose at CVPR 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_cv23/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PyPose at CVPR 2023" /><published>2023-06-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cvpr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_cv23/"><![CDATA[<p>A paper <a href="https://openaccess.thecvf.com/content/CVPR2023/html/Wang_PyPose_A_Library_for_Robot_Learning_With_Physics-Based_Optimization_CVPR_2023_paper.html">PyPose: A Library for Robot Learning With Physics-Based Optimization</a> has been presented in the past CVPR 2023 conference.  This is an effort made by a large team of developers, led by Dr. <a href="https://sairlab.org/">Chen Wang</a> from SUNY Buffalo, with people from <a href="https://theairlab.org/">CMU</a>, <a href="https://lucacarlone.mit.edu/">MIT</a>, <a href="https://personal.ntu.edu.sg/elhxie/">NTU</a>, <a href="https://rsl.ethz.ch/">ETHZ</a>, etc., and of course we Penn State, with our colleague Dr. <a href="aerogjy.github.io">Junyi Geng</a>.</p>

<p>In a nutshell, PyPose enables the <strong>full-stack, end-to-end differentiable learning</strong> for robotic applications.  One key challenge in robotic learning is the effective representation of poses, i.e., orientations and positions of robots, that requires the usage of Lie group; PyPose is a unique library that bakes Lie group into PyTorch in the robotic context.  In this effort, in collaboration with Dr. Geng, we contributed functionalities and applications on the control and system side.</p>

<p>For more information, see its <a href="pypose.org">official website</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2306_3.jpeg" width="1000" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A paper PyPose: A Library for Robot Learning With Physics-Based Optimization has been presented in the past CVPR 2023 conference. This is an effort made by a large team of developers, led by Dr. Chen Wang from SUNY Buffalo, with people from CMU, MIT, NTU, ETHZ, etc., and of course we Penn State, with our colleague Dr. Junyi Geng.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Going to AIAA Aviation 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news_av23/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Going to AIAA Aviation 2023" /><published>2023-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/av23</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news_av23/"><![CDATA[<p>For the coming AIAA Aviation 2023 conference we will be presenting three papers spanning over a range of research fields, with our collaborators. Here are the summaries:</p>

<h2 id="multi-timescale-hierarchical-control">Multi-timescale hierarchical control</h2>
<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2023-4509">Graph-based Hierarchical Control of Electrified Aircraft Systems with Automated Timescale Decomposition</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Yin Yu, Seho Park, Daning Huang, <a href="http://www.paclab.info/">Herschel Pangborn</a></li>
  <li>This paper aims to address one main challenge in the <strong>energy management of electrified aircraft</strong> involving nonlinear electro-thermo-mechanical dynamics.  Hierarchical control is a potent method to control the system in an efficient and nearly optimal manner, yet it requires the knowledge of <strong>multiple timescales</strong> that are unlikely available.</li>
  <li>We developed an algorithm that leverages Koopman theory for <strong>systematic timescale decomposition</strong> of a networked dynamical system, which informs the design of a hierarchical control framework.  The whole workflow is demonstrated on an electrified unmanned aerial vehicle.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/img/post_2306_1.png" width="600" /></p>

<h2 id="modal-analysis-of-fluid-flow">Modal analysis of fluid flow</h2>
<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2023-4350">Modal Analysis of Spatiotemporal Data via Multi-fidelity Multi-variate Gaussian Processes</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Jiwoo Song, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>We identified an interesting connection between Gaussian processes (GP) and the classical dynamical mode decomposition (DMD) method via linear system theory and Koopman formalism; in some sense, both methods estimate the spectral density of the underlying system.</li>
  <li>Viewing GP as a Bayesian version of DMD, we demonstrate the robustness of GP in the presence of nonlinearity, high noise, and irregular time sampling.</li>
  <li><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1l32RVnxwMGxEUCsSvFT3bYTdicB4nSYu/view?usp=sharing">Here</a> are the 10-min slides for this paper.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/img/post_2306_2.png" width="800" /></p>

<h2 id="landing-of-evtol">Landing of eVTOL</h2>
<p><a href="https://arc.aiaa.org/doi/abs/10.2514/6.2023-3409">Precision Landing Trajectory Optimization for eVTOL Vehicles with High-Fidelity Aerodynamic Models</a></p>
<ul>
  <li>Yufei Wu, Sabrullah Deniz, Yang Shi, <a href="http://volweb.utk.edu/~zwang124/resume.html">Zhenbo Wang</a>, Daning Huang</li>
  <li>We propose a novel approach to optimal landing control of electric vertical takeoff and landing (eVTOL) vehicles for potentially wide applications such as <strong>urban air mobility (UAM)</strong>, passenger transportation, package delivery, and aircraft carrier landing missions.</li>
  <li>Particularly we aim to develop efficient algorithms that facilitate generation of <strong>accurate optimal landing trajectories</strong> for eVTOL vehicles under operational constraints considering <strong>high-fidelity aerodynamic models</strong>.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For the coming AIAA Aviation 2023 conference we will be presenting three papers spanning over a range of research fields, with our collaborators. Here are the summaries:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Department seminar by Dr. Shaowu Pan from RPI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/news/2023/04/27/pan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Department seminar by Dr. Shaowu Pan from RPI" /><published>2023-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/news/2023/04/27/pan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/news/2023/04/27/pan/"><![CDATA[<p>We hosted Dr. <a href="http://www.shaowupan.com/">Shaowu Pan</a> from  Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute for a seminar in our department.  Dr. Pan’s expertise lies in the intersection between computational fluid dynamics, data-driven modeling of complex systems, scientific machine learning, and dynamical systems.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract</strong> Fluid dynamics exhibits complex, multi-scale spatial structure, chaotic dynamics in time, and bifurcation in the relevant parameters. Among these challenges, spatial complexity is the major barrier to modeling and control of fluid dynamics, which motivates the need for dimensionality reduction. Existing paradigms, such as proper orthogonal decomposition or convolutional autoencoders, both struggle to accurately and efficiently represent flow structures for problems requiring variable geometry, nonuniform grid resolution (e.g., wall-bounded flows, flow phenomenon induced by small geometry features), adaptive mesh refinement, or parameter-dependent meshes. To resolve these difficulties, we propose Neural Implicit Flow (NIF) as a general framework that enables a compact and flexible dimension reduction of large-scale, parametric, spatial-temporal data into mesh-agnostic fixed-length representations. This work complements existing meshless methods, e.g., physics-informed neural networks, and we focus specifically on obtaining reduced coordinates where modeling and control tasks may be performed more efficiently. We apply our mesh-agnostic approach to several fluid flows, including flow past a cylinder, sea surface temperature data, and 3D homogeneous isotropic turbulence. In these examples, we demonstrate the utility of NIF for parametric surrogate modeling, efficient differential query in space, learning non-linear manifolds, and the interpretable low-rank decomposition of fluid flow data.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daning Huang</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="Seminar" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We hosted Dr. Shaowu Pan from Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute for a seminar in our department. Dr. Pan’s expertise lies in the intersection between computational fluid dynamics, data-driven modeling of complex systems, scientific machine learning, and dynamical systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Regional Heatwave Prediction Using Graph Neural Network and Weather Station Data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/rsch_heat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regional Heatwave Prediction Using Graph Neural Network and Weather Station Data" /><published>2023-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/heat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/rsch_heat/"><![CDATA[<p>This work is in collaboration with Dr. <a href="https://publish.illinois.edu/urban-climate/group-members/">Ashish Sharma</a>’s group at University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, and Dr. <a href="https://sustainability-innovation.asu.edu/person/zhihua-wang/">Zhi-Hua Wang</a> at Arizona State University. It marks a new field of application for our <a href="/rsch_dgn/">Geometric Deep Learning</a> approach, and demonstrates its strength in making fast, accurate, and interpretable online-predictions of complex dynamical system on graphs, such as a weather system.</p>

<p>Understanding the occurrence and propagation of <strong>regional heatwaves</strong> is of vital importance to mitigate the consequence of heat extremes. A low-cost, accurate, and timely prediction algorithm for regional heatwaves is desirable. In this study, we use the measurement data set collected from the ground weather stations, together with graph-based deep learning algorithm, to predict the occurrence of regional heatwaves in the lower 48 states of the U.S. The prediction model is trained by the daily weather observations from 91 weather stations and <strong>achieves over 90% accuracy</strong> in validation. In addition, we extract the spatiotemporal patterns of the climate dynamics learned by the deep learning model to facilitate the interpretation of the results. The proposed modeling framework can be applied to predict other types of extreme events, such as extreme precipitation, drought, and compounded events. The analysis of the model structure will also enhance our understanding of the causal inference between climate regions in the U.S. from a brand-new deep learning perspective.</p>

<p><img src="/img/post_2304_2.png" width="900" /></p>

<p>For more details see our paper <a href="https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2023GL103405">GRL2023</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Yin Yu</name></author><category term="news" /><category term="research" /><category term="Publication" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This work is in collaboration with Dr. Ashish Sharma’s group at University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, and Dr. Zhi-Hua Wang at Arizona State University. It marks a new field of application for our Geometric Deep Learning approach, and demonstrates its strength in making fast, accurate, and interpretable online-predictions of complex dynamical system on graphs, such as a weather system.]]></summary></entry></feed>